The database has been built, and some data
has been entered. Now let’s retrieve the
information we will need to build reports. We do
this by building queries, questions we ask of the
information. As we go through this domain, try
to understand when you would use each keyword in
building queries. The majority of queries one will
run in a database will use two or more tables.
The whole purpose of having a relational database
is to store data efficiently across tables
and then bring data from those tables together
using queries. For this example, we are going
to build a query that retrieves information from
both the Sales.Customer and Sales.SalesOrderHeader
tables. I have a SELECT statement started that
has columns from both these tables, and so far,
the FROM line indicates that we are just
selecting data from the Sales.Customer table.
To add the Sales.SalesOrderHeader table,
we need a JOIN statement. I will type,
JOIN Sales.SalesOrderHeader
on Sales.Customer.CustomerID =
Sales.SalesOrderHeader.CustomerID as the
field used to relate these two tables is
CustomerID. CustomerID is the primary
key in the Sales.Customer table and is
a foreign key in the Sales.SalesOrderHeader
table. Before running this, here is a fairly
common problem with a join: The CustomerID and
AccountNumber columns both have red squiggly
lines under them. When hovering the mouse over
each, we see that the column name is ambiguous,
meaning it is in both tables. In these
situations, we need to specify which table
we want to represent for each column. I will add
Sales.Customer. in front of both of these columns.
I will now execute this, and we have just over
31000 records involving customers and their
orders. We just ran what is called an inner join,
which is a join in which records will only display
if the value of the join field is in both tables.
To put this an easier way, as the CustomerID
field is the one used to join these two tables,
records will only show if the customer ID appears
in both tables. However, what if we want to see
all of the customers from the customer table?
For that, we need an outer join, and there
are three types of outer joins we can use:
left, right, and full outer joins. To determine
what join we should use, we first want to figure
out the table with all the records we want to
see. In this case, it would be Sales.Customer.
Secondly, which table is left and which is
right? Between the two tables used in a join,
the table on the left is listed first.
That would be Sales.Customer in this case.
Thus, we want a left outer join.
I will add the words LEFT OUTER
to the join and notice that we have about 700
more records than before when executing this,
indicating that we have 700 or so customers who
have never placed an order. To see the other joins
working, I will change this join from a left outer
join to a right outer join and execute this again.
The number of records reverts to the same number
as the inner join, which is good because the
right table is this Sales.SalesOrderHeader table.
Should there be any customer IDs
from this table if they do not exist
in the Sales.Customer table? The answer is
no. Though not all customers place orders,
customers should exist before they place orders.
If you need to see both customers that have not
placed orders and customers that have sales
but no definition in the Sales.Customer table,
you can use a full outer join, as I am building
here. Normally you would only use this after
combining two datasets into one, and you want to
see mismatched records from both tables in a join.
I will execute this, and we are back to showing
all customers, including ones with no orders.